<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles.atom"/>
  <title>Air Plant City - Air Plant Care</title>
  <updated>2021-06-23T15:25:17-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Air Plant City</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-tillandsia-ionantha</id>
    <published>2021-06-23T15:25:17-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-23T16:06:52-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-tillandsia-ionantha"/>
    <title>Air Plant Highlight: Tillandsia Ionantha</title>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Chorneyko</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Tillandsia Ionantha is a staple air plant with its eye-catching colors and shape. What starts off as a small collection of green or silver leaves grows into a stunning air plant displaying colorful shoots and flowers. Ionantha are known to grow purple shoots that produce yellow or white flowers.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-tillandsia-ionantha">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tillandsia Ionantha is a staple air plant with its eye-catching colors and shape. What starts off as a small collection of green or silver leaves grows into a stunning air plant displaying colorful shoots and flowers. Ionantha are known to grow purple shoots that produce yellow or white flowers. When the plant is blooming like this, its leaves can also change color to take on pink or red hues. These colors are part of what gives <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-small-plant-variety-set-of-5-plants" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia ionantha" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha</a> its nickname, “the blushing bride air plant".</span></p>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG_1005.jpg?v=1624474542" alt="air plant tillandsia ionantha" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: right;" width="318" height="212"></div>
<p>  </p>
<div style="text-align: right;"></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Aside from this plant’s unique colors and beautiful appearance, another interesting fact about Tillandsia Ionantha is that it is an epiphytic species, meaning it </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">obtains its nutrients and moisture from the air around it through its leaves instead of through soil. This also means it has the ability to grow on other plants or tree branches. Because Ionantha is an epiphytic plant, it should not be potted the way most plants would be. Displaying your plant in a glass terrarium is a good way to make sure it has enough space. Plus, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ionantha is a great addition to any plant lover’s collection because their colors and containers add a dynamic design element to any space. </span></p>
<p> </p>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG_1002.jpg?v=1624474369" alt="air plant tillandsia ionantha" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: right;" width="318" height="212"></div>
<div style="text-align: right;"></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tillandsia Ionantha is native throughout Mexico, the Carribean and Central and South America. These plants originate from many places, resulting in several varieties of Ionantha. These varieties, or eco-types, are all a little different based on the varying climates, altitudes and environments in their native zones. Examples of different varieties that we sell include <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-mexican-air-plants?variant=32948435651" target="_blank" title="tillandsia ionantha mexican" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha Mexican</a>, <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-rubra-air-plants?variant=32948496579" target="_blank" title="tillandsia ionantha rubra" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha Rubra</a>, <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-scaposa-kolbii-air-plants?variant=32948592771" target="_blank" title="tillandsia ionantha scaposa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha Scaposa</a>, <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-guatemala-air-plants?variant=32947759299" target="_blank" title="tillandsia ionantha gutemala" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha Guatemalan</a>, and <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-ionantha-fuego-air-plants?variant=32947380291" target="_blank" title="tillandsia ionantha fuego" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tillandsia Ionantha Fuego</a>.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Out of this list, Ionantha Scaposa grow the largest, and are found in higher elevations in Central America. Ionantha Guatemala (also called Ionantha Ionantha) is generally found in lower, hotter and dryer climates. Ionantha Rubra is found in comparatively more humid climates compared to that of Ionantha Guatemala (but at a similar elevation). However, each varietal is quite forgiving to </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">temperature and water. </span>Because of these plants’ vast origins, they are tolerant of many conditions. Many people are attracted to Ionantha for their low-maintenance upkeep. Ionantha are known to be generally healthy plants, so they typically do well with a routine misting or soaking a few times a week.</p>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG_1151_84dbee4b-4295-44c4-a1be-3a4353710fbe.jpg?v=1624476424" alt="air plant tillandsia ionantha" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: right;" width="317" height="211"></div>
<p>  </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When it comes to light, Ionantha need just the right amount of light to allow them to flower without drying out. Indirect sunlight is recommended for these plants, but be sure they aren’t completely covered by shade. Also consider the temperature and air circulation of your plant’s location. These plants need good air circulation to encourage blooming, and they do best in warm temperatures between 60 and 80 degrees Fahrenheit. Tillandsia Ionantha is an exciting plant to care for. Healthy plants will reward you with a colorful bloom! </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/spanish-moss-air-plant</id>
    <published>2021-05-20T11:40:41-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-23T16:12:16-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/spanish-moss-air-plant"/>
    <title>Air Plant Highlight: Spanish Moss</title>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Chorneyko</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span><span>One of the most common yet unique air plants found here in the United States is the Tillandsia Usneoides, better known as Spanish Moss. </span></span><meta charset="utf-8"><span>Contradicting its name, Spanish Moss is neither Spanish nor moss but is a bromeliad that is indigenous to regions of Central and South America, parts of the Caribbean, and southern United States.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/spanish-moss-air-plant">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG_9699_480x480.jpg?v=1621526060" alt="air plant tillandsia spanish moss care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: right;" width="242" height="303"></div>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">What is Spanish Moss?</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the most common yet unique air plants found here in the United States is the Tillandsia Usneoides, better known as <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/packs-of-3-6-or-9-spanish-moss-tillandsia-usneoides-strands-live-save-40?variant=31920315793507" target="_blank" title="spanish moss air plant tillandsia " rel="noopener noreferrer">Spanish Moss</a>. If you are native to the South or have visited cities such as Charleston, New Orleans, Savannah, or even our hometown of Saint Augustine, then you have probably set eyes on these whimsical, flowing strands from the ancient live oaks or swamp-loving cypress trees.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Contradicting its name, Spanish Moss is neither Spanish nor moss but is a bromeliad that is indigenous to regions of Central and South America, parts of the Caribbean, and southern United States. The name was given to this plant when French explorers recognized the resemblance of the tillandsia to the beards of Spanish Conquistadors, hence naming it “Spanish Beard” which led to “Spanish Moss”. Today the air plant is most often known for its aesthetic qualities and use in plant arrangements, but it has also historically been known for its use as mulch, insulation, and stuffing for mattresses and even automobile upholstery. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Is it a live plant?</span></h3>
<div style="text-align: right;"></div>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Along with other species of air plants, Spanish Moss is an epiphyte, and it collects minerals and nutrients needed for survival from the surrounding air and rainwater through its trichomes, the fuzzy hair-like substances seen on the strands. The Southern Live Oaks and Bald Cypress trees create the perfect habitat for the Spanish Moss as they have high rates of foliar mineral leaching of calcium, magnesium, potassium, and phosphorus. Although the Spanish Moss relies on the trees for such nutrition, they are not parasitic to them as they only use the trees for support and not to draw in nutrients.  </span></p>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/DSC00805_480x480.jpg?v=1621524302" alt="air plant tillandsia spanish moss care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: right;" width="251" height="377"></div>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Will mine have bugs in it?</span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">If you are familiar with Spanish Moss in the wild, then you have probably been warned of the pests it may contain such as chiggers or red bugs. This is a common concern among customers who are considering purchasing the Spanish Moss. We are happy to assure you, however, that all our Spanish Moss is grown in a controlled greenhouse environment and is routinely treated for pests.</span>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Do I Take Care of It?</span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Caring for Spanish Moss is very simple and similar to <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-care" target="_blank" title="spanish moss air plant tillandsia care" rel="noopener noreferrer">caring for other species of air plants</a>. Proper hydration and plenty of air circulation are the key factors in providing a happy home for your Spanish Moss. Soaking in rainwater weekly is ideal, but frequent misting will also do the trick and will help prevent breakage. Providing bright, indirect light and partial sun in a warm area either indoors or outdoors is preferable. Direct, hot sun will dry the moss. </span><br><span style="font-weight: 400;"> <br>Now that you know the odds and ends of this eccentric and admired species of Tillandsia, you can grow the Spanish Moss yourself and use it in your air plant and succulent designs! The sky is the limit when decorating and you will really enjoy adding dimension, color contrast, and scale to your designs and projects. </span>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-care-killing-hurting</id>
    <published>2021-05-14T11:37:47-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-17T14:04:58-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-care-killing-hurting"/>
    <title>What’s Killing My Air Plants?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Chorneyko</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Keeping any kind of plant alive can be difficult, especially for those who aren’t gifted with a natural green thumb. Luckily air plants are generally on the low maintenance side. These care tips will help your plants thrive!</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-care-killing-hurting">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">How to Water, Fertilize, and Tend to Your Air Plants </span></h2>
<p>Keeping any kind of plant alive can be difficult, especially for those who aren’t gifted with a natural green thumb. Luckily air plants are generally on the low maintenance side. These care tips will help your plants thrive!</p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Over or Under Watering–Yes, air plants do need water!</span></h3>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/BRB1824_480x480.jpg?v=1621005997" alt="air plant tillandsia care watering" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; float: right;" width="459" height="306"></div>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s possible to under-water your air plant. The best way to fully hydrate your plant is to remove it from its container, soak it for 20-30 minutes, shake off the excess water, and then let it dry for a few hours before returning it to its container, vessel or display. Your air plant will likely stay its healthiest if watered this way once a week, but each plant is unique. One indication that your plant might need some water is if its leaves are curled or folded rather than open and flat. Something else to keep in mind is that different air plant species will display their hydration differently. <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-aeranthos-air-plants?variant=33441358979" target="_blank" title="Air plant tillandsia aeranthos care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Aeranthos</a> or <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/everything-except-wholesale/products/tillandsia-tenufolia-air-plants?_pos=1&amp;_sid=9d885c6b5&amp;_ss=r&amp;variant=32950212867" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care Tenuifolia" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tenuifolia</a>, for example, show a dramatic curl depending on its water intake. On the other hand, species like <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/air-plant-combinations/products/air-plant-combination-of-5-tillandsia-ionanthas-5-small-small-plants" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care ionantha" rel="noopener noreferrer">lonanthas</a> might not show such a dramatic change. </span><br><span style="font-weight: 400;">Air plants can die from being over-watered, too. Plants should be fully dried before being soaked in water again. Your plant can also rot from moisture if returned to an enclosed space before they fully dry, but avoiding these things will keep your plant healthy!</span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Exposure to Salt and Chemicals</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you have potted plants in your house, and over time you have noticed a white crust on the top, your municipal water likely has a lot of added salts and chlorine. In the air plants, these additives manifest themselves as white crust along the tips of the plants’ leaves. It is especially noticeable in Ionanthas where you may see tiny salt crystals hanging from the end of the leaves. Since air plants don’t rest in soil there is nothing to filter the salt, making it especially harmful to air plants. The salt that deposits on the air plant’s leaves can prevent water and nutrient absorption, ultimately suffocating the plant.  The salt deposits typically come from municipal water, so this is not the best water to use when hydrating your plant. Instead, try rain, well, pond, lake, or non-carbonated mineral water. </span></p>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">If you think your tillandsia is suffering from salt deposits, this is one time where we recommend a long soak in distilled water. This will help to wash away the excess salt build-up! Make sure to not confuse salt-build up to trichomes. Read about trichomes <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-trichomes" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care trichomes" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>!</span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Heat and Light Exposure </span></h3>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/DSC00097_480x480.jpg?v=1621006527" alt="air plant tillandsia care killing" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; float: right;" width="254" height="169"></div>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Air plants can become dehydrated when they are exposed to hot, direct sunlight. Sitting next to a hot window or in a hot room can even cause the leaves of your plant to burn! An easy way to determine whether or not the conditions are right for your plant is if you are comfortable in those conditions. Most tillandsia plants are happiest in the 55-85 degree range. Some plants like <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-xerographica-air-plants?variant=30410105847907" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care xerographica" rel="noopener noreferrer">Xerographica</a>, <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/tillandsia-harrisii-air-plants?variant=34075918211" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care harrisii" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harisii</a>, and <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/premium-air-plants/products/tillandsia-stricta-hybrid-air-plants?_pos=1&amp;_sid=df2bb23e2&amp;_ss=r&amp;variant=32949637123" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care stricta" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stricta</a> are adapted to hotter temperatures. These are called <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-nutritional-needs-and-fertilizer?_pos=1&amp;_sid=1a180b644&amp;_ss=r" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care how to" rel="noopener noreferrer">Xeric plants</a>.</span><br><span style="font-weight: 400;">On a similar note, air plants can also receive too little light. Your plant needs indirect natural light or bright artificial light for several hours a day. Plants that are left in darker parts of your home will probably have a much shorter lifespan than those receiving the necessary amount of light. </span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Extreme Temperatures</span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">While many air plants naturally grow at high elevations, it is not likely they will do well in freezing temperatures. Typically, any temperature below 32 degrees Fahrenheit is intolerable for air plants. There are some exceptions to this, such as the <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/everything-except-wholesale/products/tillandsia-usneoides-strands-spanish-moss?_pos=1&amp;_sid=5acb50a83&amp;_ss=r&amp;variant=32950384643" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care spanish moss" rel="noopener noreferrer">Spanish Moss</a> found from Texas to Florida that can withstand temperatures as low as the twenties. Commercially sold air plants would likely not survive in temperatures this low, however. If your plants live outdoors, we recommend moving them inside if temperatures fall below 45 degrees Fahrenheit. </span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fertilizer Burn </span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">High concentration of <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/rustic-wood-vines/products/air-plant-bromeliad-fertilizer-packet-one-year-supply?_pos=2&amp;_sid=b35964bc4&amp;_ss=r&amp;variant=32913058819" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care fertilizer " rel="noopener noreferrer">fertilizer</a> and too frequent fertilizing can burn your air plants. We recommend diluting your fertilizer with water, then soaking plants in the fertilizer water once a month. If you prefer to mist your plants with water instead of soaking, just add fertilizer to your routine. Be cautious about mixing and diluting the fertilizer before spraying your plants. </span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Moisture and Poor Air Circulation </span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Some air plants like high humidity, but most prefer cool and dry conditions like those of the deserts or highlands where air plants often originate. Because of this, air plants should always be dried off quickly after being soaked. One easy way to do this is placing your air plant under a ceiling fan to avoid moisture that leaves air plants susceptible to rotting. If you choose to mist your plant for watering, it's still best to remove the plant from its container to make sure it fully dries. Hanging plants, like living Spanish Moss, should be given full circulation on all sides, and not pressed flat against a wall or surface.</span><br>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Their Natural Life Cycle </span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An air plant’s life cycle includes growth, blooming, and reproduction by the pups and seedlings. Some air plants can even bloom multiple times per year. Eventually, the mother plant will exert most of her energy into producing small offset plants, and by the time the mother plant is done reproducing, the offsets are close to the size of their mother plant. The mother plant will eventually die but the organism lives on through the offsets. When an air plant starts to produce offsets there are a few options. You can divide the air plants or you can let the plants naturally clump.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For more information on general air plant care, check out our other popular blog: <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-care" target="_blank" title="air plant care how to tillandsia" rel="noopener noreferrer">How To Care For Tillandsia</a>.</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/how-trim-air-plant-tillandsia-roots</id>
    <published>2021-05-07T13:48:28-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-19T16:53:02-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/how-trim-air-plant-tillandsia-roots"/>
    <title>To Trim or Not to Trim Air Plant Roots</title>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Chorneyko</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>It is true, air plants do have roots! Air plant roots are completely natural. Due to live plant import restrictions, air plants are required to be trimmed at their original export farm–typically West Indies, Mexico and South America. This is why your air plants normally arrive root-less but it does not harm the plants.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/how-trim-air-plant-tillandsia-roots">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span style="font-weight: 400;">Tillandsia, or more commonly known as air plants, are loved by all due to their aesthetic nature and soil-free houseplant reputation. But wait, then why are they growing roots? It is true, air plants do have roots! Air plant roots are completely natural. Due to live plant import restrictions, air plants are required to be trimmed at their original export farm–typically West Indies, Mexico and South America. This is why your air plants normally arrive root-less but it does not harm the plants. However, it does make for some confusion when the roots grow back when they seemingly had none.</span>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">How do Air Plants Get Nutrients Without Roots?</span></h3>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG_5868_480x480.jpg?v=1620410372" alt="air plant tillandsia care roots" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; float: right;" width="403" height="268"></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Air plants are part of the unique plant family known as epiphytes–Greek word “epi” (meaning ‘upon’) and “python” (meaning ‘plant’). Epiphytes are plants that grow or attach themselves on other plants for support. They are not parasitic plants–meaning plants that acquire some or all of their nutrients from another living plant. Contrary to most plants that get nutrients from their roots in soil, air plants’ root systems are only used to attach and anchor themselves to tree trunks, branches, rocks, etc. Roots are necessary for air plant survival in the wild because they keep air plants off the ground away from animals, tumultuous weather and other threats! Nevertheless, when air plants function as decor, roots are not mandatory and may be removed without compromising the health of the plant. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Think of roots like hair! It is still growing all the time but it is technically dead. And people can decide how long or short they want to keep it – just like air plant roots! </span></p>
<p>Air plants receive nutrients through their leaves from light and moisture in the air. Over time, air plants developed trichomes on their leaves to catch and absorb nutrients. Trichomes–Greek word “trichoma” (meaning ‘hair growth’)–are the white, crystal-like hairs on the leaves that are visible on most air plant species. Another well-known plant with trichomes is marijuana–but don’t eat or smoke your air plants!</p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">How to Trim Your Air Plant</span></h3>
<div style="text-align: right;"></div>
<div style="text-align: right;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/DSC00602_b4f04f19-cd6f-4275-a5f3-ef02105129be_480x480.jpg?v=1620409537" alt="air plant tillandsia root care" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; float: right;" width="397" height="298"></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So now you have the choice–do you want to keep your air plants au naturale with growing roots or trim them for a clean, defined look? Most enthusiasts that keep their plants inside prefer a cleaner look but those living in warmer, humid climates have the option to keep them outside where they can naturally root to a tree. Just like the plant itself, the roots will continue to grow and will need a trim every so often if that is what you choose to do. You can easily trim your air plants with small kitchen scissors or cuticle scissors–but not too close to the base of the plant, as it can cause damage! While trimming the roots you can also remove dried leaves to clean-up the base and help avoid trapping water and humidity which causes rot.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because of their soil-free nature, air plants prevail as the superior houseplant–their versatility is unmatched. The possibilities are endless! Now that you know about air plant roots and how they get nutrients, will you trim the air plant roots or let them grow out?</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/mothers-day-gifts-air-plants</id>
    <published>2021-04-20T14:42:17-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:58:18-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/mothers-day-gifts-air-plants"/>
    <title>Our Top Picks for Mother&apos;s Day Gifts!</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Mother’s Day is right around the corner–hint, hint! Luckily we curated a short list of the perfect air plant gifts for any and all types of moms. If you need more inspiration, we have a </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span>gift collection</span></a><span> with even more options.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/mothers-day-gifts-air-plants">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">It's Almost Mother's Day!</span></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Mother’s Day is right around the corner–hint, hint! Luckily we curated a short list of the perfect air plant gifts for any and all types of moms. If you need more inspiration, we have a </span>
<a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">gift collection</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> with even more options. Additionally, as if you needed more convincing, air plants are the perfect gift because they are beautiful and low maintenance plus, they last longer than traditional cut flowers! Check out our </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-care" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">air plant care page</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to learn more about watering, lighting and more.</span>
<br><br>
<!--block right image-->
<div class="b-row" style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; flex-direction: row; align-items: center; align-content: center;">
  <div class="b-col" style="flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <h3><span style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/geometric-pendant-hanger-with-assorted-air-plant" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer">1. Hanging Metal Pendants with Assorted Air Plants</a> </span></span></h3>
    <span style="font-weight: 400;">Our handcrafted diamond pendants are a unique way to suspend any small to medium tillandsia–and it already comes with one hand-picked, assorted plant. The black iron pendant will not rust or discolor from moisture as they are dipped in plant-safe sealant. Hang them with fishing line for a floating appearance or with twine to create a more natural vibe. This gift is also very cost effective at only $8.95 plus shipping–so much so that rounding up to our </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/products/trio-of-geometric-pendants-hangers-with-assorted-air-plants?pr_prod_strat=description&amp;pr_rec_pid=4386969583715&amp;pr_ref_pid=4386980954211&amp;pr_seq=uniform&amp;variant=31559650181219" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">three pack of pedants</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to create a balanced display is a feasible option at $23.90 plus shipping!</span>
  </div>
  <div class="b-col" style="text-align: center; flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_geometric_iron_pendant_12_480x480.jpg?v=1618937675" alt="Air Plant City Gift Mother's Day" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px;" width="316" height="auto">
  </div>
</div>
<!--end block-->
<!--block left image-->
<div class="b-row" style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; flex-direction: row; align-items: center; align-content: center;">
  <div class="b-col" style="text-align: center; flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_white_ceramic_pot_1_480x480.jpg?v=1618937914" alt="Air Plant City Gift Mother's Day" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; " width="342" height="auto">
  </div>
  <div class="b-col" style="flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <h3><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/trio-of-white-geometric-ceramic-containers-with-assorted-air-plants?variant=29633638072419" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer">2. White Geometric Ceramic Containers with Large Assorted Air Plants </a> </span></h3>
   <span style="font-weight: 400;">These 20 sided-geometric containers are a customer favorite because they are fun and funky! The glossy ceramic makes for a balanced contrast to the natural colors of the large air plants that come in the pack. We love placing these containers on windowsills and coffee tables to add a pop of bright white! Our three pack of ceramic containers with three large air plants are currently $23.90!</span>
  </div> 
</div>
<!--end block-->
<!--block right image-->
<div class="b-row" style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; flex-direction: row; align-items: center; align-content: center;">
  <div class="b-col" style="flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <h3><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/stunning-air-plant-terrariums-kits-complete-with-stones-moss-and-vibrant-air-plants" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer">3. Stunning Air Plant Terrariums with Red Abdita</a> </span></h3>
    <span style="font-weight: 400;">This spectacular pack of three blown-glass terrariums–about four inches wide and four and a half inches tall–come with air plants, reindeer moss and river stones. Terrarium kits are foolproof gifts for the mom that is crafty and loves DIY. Plus, building the terrarium together is a sweet gesture for a post-Mother’s day activity! This gift is extremely versatile with flat bottoms and a hook on top so they can be displayed on a flat surface or hung from the ceiling. Buy now on sale for only $29.95 plus shipping!</span>
  </div>
  <div class="b-col" style="text-align: center; flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_glass_terrarium_8_480x480.jpg?v=1618938117" alt="Air Plant City Gift Mother's Day" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px; " width="333" height="auto">
  </div>
</div>
<!--end block-->
<!--block left image-->
<div class="b-row" style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; flex-direction: row; align-items: center; align-content: center;">
  <div class="b-col" style="text-align: center; flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/Airplants_tillandsia_containers3jpg_480x480.jpg?v=1618938178" alt="Air Plant City Gift Mother's Day" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px;" width="316" height="auto">
  </div>
  <div class="b-col" style="flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <h3><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/wooden-driftwood-container-with-a-mini-xerographica-air-plant?variant=35707908803" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer">4. Driftwood Container with Mini Xerographica</a> </span></h3>
   <span style="font-weight: 400;">Our driftwood containers come in size </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/trio-of-wooden-driftwood-containers-with-harisii-streptophylla-and?variant=35833248707" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">small</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> or </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/trio-of-large-wooden-driftwood-containers-with-assorted-large-air-plants?variant=31055878586467" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">large</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and come with assorted small or large air plants. The containers come as individuals or three or six packs meaning you can customize your gift based on budget and your mother’s preference. The containers are a beautiful light wash driftwood which give off a modern yet neutral feel–the perfect addition to any decor!</span>
  </div> 
</div>
<!--end block-->
<!--block right image-->
<div class="b-row" style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; flex-direction: row; align-items: center; align-content: center;">
  <div class="b-col" style="flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <h3><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/best-selling-plants-gifts/products/air-plant-grab-bag-of-10-small-medium-tillandsias?variant=34216866819" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer">5. Air Plant Grab Bag of Small, Medium or Large Air Plants</a> </span></h3>
    <span style="font-weight: 400;">If your mom already has plenty of options to place and decorate with air plants, our most popular grab bag of small, medium or large air plants is the gift you’ve been searching for! It comes as a bundle of ten, twenty or thirty–the more you get, the more you save. Plus, we pick out the best air plants in stock so we do the hard part for you! The pack will include at least six different varieties. Add on a one year supply of </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/air-plant-bromeliad-fertilizer-packet-one-year-supply?variant=32913058819" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">air plant fertilizer packet</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for just $4.75 plus shipping!</span>
  </div>
  <div class="b-col" style="text-align: center; flex: 1 1 200px; width:100%;">
    <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplantcity_tillandsia_airplants-Variety-Pack-176_480x480.jpg?v=1618938217" alt="Air Plant City Gift Mother's Day" style="margin: 10px 10px 10px 10px;" width="327" height="auto">
  </div>
</div>
<!--end block-->
<p><br><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re still not sure which air plant and accessory is perfect for your mother, consider giving them the gift of choice through a </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/shop-air-plants/products/gift-card?variant=33397780483" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">gift card</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to Air Plant City! That way they can receive exactly what they want for Mother’s Day.</span></p>
<p><br><span style="font-weight: 400;">At Air Plant City, we are dedicated to providing fast and quality air plants and accessories. If you are not completely satisfied with the health and vitality of your air plants, we will replace them at no cost to you. Check out our 30 day </span><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-guarantee" target="_blank" title="Mother's Day gifts air plant city giftable" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">guarantee</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">! Happy Mother's Day!</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-pollination-reproduction</id>
    <published>2019-07-31T14:34:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-14T16:17:32-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-pollination-reproduction"/>
    <title>Air Plant Pollination &amp; Reproduction</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Plants get pollinated and so do the air plants. You're probably wondering how this works for them. Well, in the rainforests they’re pollinated by birds, wind, and insects that come in contact with them.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-pollination-reproduction">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Plants get pollinated and so do the air plants. You're probably wondering how this works for them. Well, in the rainforests they’re pollinated by birds, wind, and insects that come in contact with them. They can also self-pollinate, which is when there's a transfer of pollen from the stamen of a plant to its stigma.</p>
<p>In the tropical rainforests, bees, night moths, hummingbirds, and ants (generally referred to as pollinators) play the role of cross-pollinating an air plant with another of the same species during movement or feeding. This turns out quite helpful for the “self-incompatible’ Tillandsia species (T. caput-medusae and T. streptophylla) that can’t self-pollinate.</p>
<p>Today, we have hybrids of Tillandsia that have been exquisitely created through the cross-pollination of two different species by hybridizers. For example, T. Redy is a hybrid of T. Streptophylla X T. Concolor (developed by Mark Dimmitt) and T. John Arden's Art, a hybrid of T. intermedia X .T. capitata marron (developed by John Arden). Quite interesting, don’t you think?</p>
<p>After blooming, the cycle of life for the air plants continues and there's the production of seeds and offsets/pups as a result. For seed pods to be formed, the flowers need to be pollinated else your plants just end up growing offsets/pups alone. Hence, you shouldn't worry about pollinating your air plants as they don’t need it to grow pups.</p>
<p>Some air plants produce only one pup and some can produce up to ten pups. In some air plants species, the adult plant would produce a few generations of pups/offsets before dying, however many air plants species will bloom just once and hence, have just one generation of seeds or offsets/pups.</p>
<p>Flowers have generally adapted to possess bright colors and scents for attracting pollinators such as bees or hummingbirds to them. Besides species like the T. Diaguitensis, T. duratii, T. straminea and some others, most air plants lack scents but still make up for this with their bright colored flowers that come in handy in attracting pollinators to them.</p>
<p>Want to know if your air plants got pollinated? Simple, you’d notice seed pods forming in place of the flowers after blooming. These seed pods contain Tillandsia seeds encased in fluffy hairs that are known as COMA or parachute. Over time (which might be between three months to about two years), the seed pods would develop and the walls of the pod would split and release the seeds as a result. The COMA is designed to travel just like a parachute gliding through the air. Since they’re hairy and the hairs are very coarse, they’d find it easy to attach themselves to new plants, trees or rocks and start germinating in their new location.</p>
<p>In the wild, air plants produce seeds before the rainy season and would need to stay wet so as to start germinating and could die off in drought periods.</p>
<p>A lot of patience and prudence is needed when it comes to growing air plants from seed stage, so enjoy the journey.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/why-air-plants-dont-need-soil</id>
    <published>2019-07-31T14:31:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-14T16:30:47-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/why-air-plants-dont-need-soil"/>
    <title>Why Air Plants Don&apos;t Need Soil</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Like all plants, air plants have leaves, roots, and bloom but don't need soil to grow. Why? That's because air plants, aka Tillandsia, come from the family of epiphytes.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/why-air-plants-dont-need-soil">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Like all plants, air plants have leaves, roots, and bloom but don't need soil to grow. Why? That's because air plants, aka Tillandsia, come from the family of epiphytes and this means, instead of growing from the soil, they anchor themselves to other plants without being parasitic or causing harm. You're likely to find them on tree trunks in tropical rainforests as the tree’s canopy shades them from the sun, giving them filtered sunlight exposure.</p>
<p>An air plant's roots are meant for anchorage to another plant and not for absorbing nutrients or water like soil-needy plants. So, how do they survive? Well, these plants have trichomes (tiny scales) on their leaves for nutrients and water absorption.</p>
<p>In a tropical rainforest that’s densely populated, there’s usually a harsh competition for light, air, nutrients, and water. To exclude themselves from this competition, epiphytes have evolved over the years and now have their root systems in the air causing them to adapt perfectly and live in a harsh environment.</p>
<p>This is why air plants don't need soil to survive since they are epiphytes. Living on trees have granted them a higher place in the forest canopy. They’re able to get enough filtered sunlight in the tree's canopy without any need to compete with other trees and vines in the wild than they would have if they were to be living in the soil.  </p>
<p>Now you ask, "If they don't need the roots, what do I do with them?" Well, without cutting the roots too close to the plants (to avoid damage), you could simply anchor or mount them onto any surface that you like for display. Something like a wreath or hanging planter isn’t a bad idea. They will have a pretty firm anchor over time and moderately strong wind can’t remove them.<br>Being a not soil-needy plant, an air plant would do just great being displayed anywhere. Yes, you're allowed to get creative or even send them as a gift to loved ones. As long as these plants get the needed filtered sunlight and good air circulation, you're good to go.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-the-blooming-process</id>
    <published>2019-07-31T14:27:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:51:57-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-the-blooming-process"/>
    <title>The Air Plant Blooming Process</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Let’s begin with some background check on the blooming process of air plants. Just like all flowering plants, they bloom at the beginning of their reproductive cycle. Here’s a fun fact for you; air plants bloom only once throughout their lifetime…amazing, right?</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-the-blooming-process">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Air plants start out as slow growers that need your patience, love and care to bloom.</p>
<p>Now you’re either asking one of these questions, “How do I make them bloom?'', "Is there a right way to nurture these air plants?” OR just waiting patiently for your <em>Tillandsia </em>to flower and wondering if you could do anything to hasten the process.</p>
<p>Sounds like you? Well, we got you covered...</p>
<p><strong>Before Blooming</strong></p>
<p>Let’s begin with some background check on the blooming process of air plants. Just like all flowering plants, they bloom at the beginning of their reproductive cycle. Here’s a fun fact for you; air plants bloom only once throughout their lifetime…amazing, right? They also produce different flowers which depend on their species. Most of these species produce beautiful flowers that come in diverse colors like pink, red, yellow and purple.</p>
<p>In the world of air plants, you’re sure to notice different bloom styles. For example, when the <em>Capitata peach</em> starts blooming, it’s pale pink in color with the flowers emerging from its center. In the case of the <em>aeranthos </em><em>and stricta, </em>small buds tend to emerge from its center which later becomes larger and releases flowers when they open up. For some species, blooming lasts only a couple of days while others could last long up to some weeks.</p>
<p>Larger air plants like the <em>caput-medusae</em> and the <em>xerographica </em>have a longer cycle when it comes to blooming. They tend to grow large flower tracts known as “inflorescence” that can surprisingly be a foot tall or over for some species. The inflorescence contains the whole flower tracts which open up for the flowers to emerge with time. Some air plants have flower tracts that can last over a year.</p>
<p><strong>After Blooming</strong></p>
<p>After your air plants have completed their blooming cycle, you’re likely to notice ‘new growth’ off the sides, at the base or find them protected under leaves that are beginning to die off [so be careful when trimming your plants]. These are plantlets called “pups” which would mature later into adult air plants and repeat the growth cycle.</p>
<p>To hasten the growth stage after blooming, you can carefully cut off the flower tract that emerged from the air plant to quicken the offset stage. After blooming, air plants [depending on the species] would produce 1 to 3 offsets or pups on average. Once the offsets reach about 1/3 the size of the adult plant, you can snip them off or leave them [they would form a clump].</p>
<p><strong>Making Your Air Plants Bloom</strong></p>
<p>As long as your <em>Tillandsia </em>is healthy they would bloom in due time, this doesn't leave out the fact that they need to be cared for and have enough sunlight exposure for this to happen. You could also take advantage of diluted fertilizers to hasten the blooming process and the production of offsets or pups.</p>
<p><strong>Nurturing Your Blooming Air Plants</strong></p>
<p>We haven’t forgotten your million dollar question, “Is there a right way to nurture these air plants?” Well, first things first, don’t ever stop watering your air plants! As expected, your blooming air plants would need a little more water than usual as the energy is needed for the flower and the production of offsets or pups. Although, when it comes to watering, you need to be careful to not get the flower wet too. Why? Because having the flower soaked in water would cause it to wilt or rot.</p>
<p>So, instead of soaking up your air plant while it's blooming, you can mist using a spray bottle or hold under mildly running water to wet only the needed parts of the air plants.</p>
<p>It's important for your air plants to remain healthy and radiant, so, do well to look after them.</p>
<p>Even if your air plants haven’t started to bloom they’re still beautiful to behold, so relax and enjoy the journey.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-nutritional-needs-and-fertilizer</id>
    <published>2019-05-14T12:35:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:39:31-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-nutritional-needs-and-fertilizer"/>
    <title>Air Plant Nutritional Needs and Fertilizer</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Air plants have ingeniously evolved over time to store significant quantities of nutrients and moisture in the leaves of their plants. This makes them incredibly durable and very easy to look after.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-nutritional-needs-and-fertilizer">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong><em>Everything you need to know about the nutritional needs of your air plants</em><em> </em></strong></p>
<p>Air plants have ingeniously evolved over time to store significant quantities of nutrients and moisture in the leaves of their plants. This makes them incredibly durable and very easy to look after.</p>
<p>If you provide your plants with access to sunlight and adequate water, then your plants are likely to receive most of the nutrients they need. This means they’re sure to be thriving in no time at all.  </p>
<p><strong><em>Air plants in the wild</em></strong></p>
<p>Air plants are generally categorized as evolving from one of two distinct climate groups – Xeric climates and Mesic climates.</p>
<p>Xeric Tillandsia – like Harrissi, tend to live in dryer climates like the southern parts of the United States. They need less water to sustain themselves. These robust plants can normally be found in desert-like environments, often near a rock formation or mountain range.</p>
<p>Mesic Tillandsia – like Streptophylla, hail from wetter climates like South America and generally need more water to survive. These plants are used to regular rain, fog, and mist. Mesic Tillandsia can be found in more humid climates, like tropical forests.</p>
<p>As these types of environment can be vastly different from one another, species of Tillandsia have evolved in different ways.</p>
<p><strong><em>Different air plant characteristics</em></strong></p>
<p>Xeric and Mesic air plants both have similar features that make up their physical attributes – such as an epidermis and hypodermis that create the plant’s skin. However, Xeric Tillandsia has evolved with thicker leaves that are better equipped to store water in times of drought.</p>
<p>Mesic Tillandsia has developed over time with thinner leaves – as they have access to a more readily available supply of water.</p>
<p>The epidermis is the outside ‘skin’ that acts as a shield to the water-storing hypodermis. As Xeric plants are equipped to store more water than mesic plants, they tend to have a thicker hypodermis.</p>
<p>Most air plants that are produced for commercial use would fall within a ‘Xeric climate’ category.</p>
<p><strong><em>Trichomes – The fuzzy white hairs on your plants</em></strong></p>
<p>Xeric Tillandsia have more trichomes - the white, hair-like fibers on the plant’s leaves - than the Mesic variety. Trichomes take in nutrients from the air and rainfall. Whilst they look like fuzzy hairs, they’re actually tiny ‘cups’ that take in water.</p>
<p>Mesic Tillandsia have fewer trichomes than their Xeric cousins. These trichomes are also more spaced out on the plant’s leaves. This is because they rely on catching water and nutrients in their axils – the space between the leaves at the base of the plant.</p>
<p>The leaves of a Tillandsia have an array of amazing ‘vascular systems’ that act to transport nutrients and moisture throughout the plant. This further highlights the way in which these plants have evolved to exist in different environments.</p>
<p><strong>What do they do with the food and water?</strong></p>
<p>Just like other plants, Tillandsia needs energy to create new plant cells that make up the body of the plant. And how is this achieved? Through a process called Photosynthesis that converts substances like sunlight, water, C02 and minerals into energy.</p>
<p>This process really kicks into gear when active radiation is taken in through the plant’s skin cells and then converted to sugar. These sugars are broken down (much like in an animal’s body) and then used to energize the plant. It’s this ‘energy’ that is used to create new leaves and sustain the plant’s health.</p>
<p>Extra energy is needed for a plant to either bloom or reproduce. In commercial environments, or simply in your backyard at home, this process can be enhanced with a fertilizer.</p>
<p><strong>What minerals do air plants need?</strong></p>
<p>Air plants are always craving essential minerals like Potassium, Nitrogen, and Phosphorous - much like other plants. Regular fertilizers have these minerals, just not in the ideal ratio for air plants.</p>
<p>Fertilizer for air plants needs to be different than regular fertilizer because air plants cannot rely on soil to break down nitrogen.</p>
<p>There are Ammoniacal and Nitrate Nitrogens that can be consumed immediately by air plants. They do not need soil to break down their properties. Special fertilizers designed for Tillandsia have just the right amount of minerals that are ideal for air plants.</p>
<p><strong>Where can I purchase air plant fertilizer?</strong></p>
<p>There is a customized water-soluble fertilizer available for purchase that is perfect for air plants. This product has been developed by Tillandsia experts across North and South America.</p>
<p>This fertilizer has been shown to improve factors like pup production and blooming cycles. All you need to do is mix the correct ratio of fertilizer to water. The mix can then easily last you a few months. You may even choose to put your fertilizer mix in a spray bottle and spray your plants that way.</p>
<p>Finally, be sure to regularly spray the leaves of your plants and give them access to lots of sunshine. If your plants are not in a location where they’re getting natural rainfall, then make sure you give them plenty of water. This will ensure that your plants radiantly bloom and produce a healthy supply of pups.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-trichomes</id>
    <published>2019-05-14T12:30:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:23:03-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-trichomes"/>
    <title>Air Plants &amp; Trichomes</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>So, you’ve just purchased a gorgeous air plant and it’s starting to flourish. Trouble is, you’ve noticed a furry substance on the leaves of your air plant. Is it mold? Or worse still, is it something that you should be really concerned about?</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-trichomes">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span></span><strong> <em>Why are my plants furry?</em></strong></p>
<p>So, you’ve just purchased a gorgeous air plant and it’s starting to flourish. Trouble is, you’ve noticed a furry substance on the leaves of your air plant. Is it mold? Or worse still, is it something that you should be really concerned about?</p>
<p>The answer to both questions is a resounding NO. You’ll be pleased to learn that the hair-like substance on the leaves of your plant is completely normal. As a matter of fact, it’s an obvious sign that you have a healthy, growing air plant.</p>
<p><strong><em>What are Trichomes?</em></strong></p>
<p>The fuzzy, white fiber on the leaves is a natural part of the plant called <em>Trichomes. </em>Trichomes give your air plants the ability to grow without soil.</p>
<p>The word Trichome is derived from the Greek word <em>Trikhoma</em> – meaning to cover with hair. </p>
<p><strong><em>What do they do?</em></strong></p>
<p>Trichomes serve several vital functions for your air plant. As root hairs, they trap and absorb water and minerals. As leaf hairs, they work to lower plant temperature, reflect radiation, and decrease water loss.</p>
<p>Trichomes can even absorb moisture from the air. This adaptation means that many air plants don’t even need regular rain.</p>
<p>Better still, Trichomes provide an invaluable defence system against pesky insects.</p>
<p><strong><em>Trichomes allow air plants to grow without soil</em></strong></p>
<p>Trichomes are crucial to Tillandsia because they act as the pathway for plants to absorb water and minerals. As Tillandsia doesn’t have root systems like other plants, it is through their trichomes that they receive everything that is needed for them to survive.</p>
<p>One such species of Tillandsia – Xerographica, utilizes its trichomes to readily absorb moisture from the air. Even though Xerographica hails from a climate that is exceptionally dry, it has evolved to flourish – thanks to its ability to source moisture from the air. </p>
<p><strong><em>Want to get your hands on a stunning air plant?</em></strong></p>
<p>There are some species of Tillandsia that have an amazing covering of trichomes. If you’d like to see a particularly hairy variety, then check out the Tillandsia Seleriana. These plants are striking in their silvery, fuzzy appearance.</p>
<p>If you love the unique look of this type of air plant, then wait until you set your eyes on other species including Ionantha Guatemala and Caput Medusae. These are sure to impress!</p>
<p>Get in touch with us today and purchase an air plant that is perfect for you.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/starting-an-air-plant-family-with-pups</id>
    <published>2019-05-14T12:09:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:29:39-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/starting-an-air-plant-family-with-pups"/>
    <title>Starting An Air Plant Family With Pups</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>How cool is it knowing that your amazing Tillandsia will someday produce their very own baby air plants! And the cutest thing about these ‘baby’ air plants is that they’re affectionately known as </span><em>pups</em><span>.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/starting-an-air-plant-family-with-pups">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong></strong><strong><em> </em></strong><strong><em>How to Propagate and Cultivate your Plants</em></strong></p>
<p>How cool is it knowing that your amazing Tillandsia will someday produce their very own baby air plants! And the cutest thing about these ‘baby’ air plants is that they’re affectionately known as pups.</p>
<p>Did you know that the number one way for air plant devotees to propagate their collection of plants is through the production of pups? That’s right, air plant lovers everywhere can cultivate their very own pup nursery. And what’s more, pups will always develop identical characteristics to their mother plant.</p>
<p><strong><em>Creating Pups</em></strong></p>
<p>Given the right conditions, all species of Tillandsia will produce pups in a relatively short space of time. It’s simply a case of knowing what features to look out for (nodes at the base of the mother plant) and when/how to make the separation between the pups and the mother plant. It’s also important to ensure that both the mother plant and pups continually receive adequate sunlight and water.</p>
<p><strong><em>How long until Pups arrive?</em></strong></p>
<p>You can expect pups to begin developing shortly after your plants first bloom cycle. It will generally take up to six months for your Tillandsia to produce its very first bloom. However, it’s worth keeping in mind that there are some species of air plant that may take several years to bloom.</p>
<p>After your plants have bloomed, that’s when the magic starts to happen. You’ll notice tiny nodes at the bottom of your plant. This means the baby plants have started to arrive!</p>
<p>During this time, it’s vital that you keep looking after the mother plant as you normally would. But remember to always be gentle with the pups. They can be quite delicate as they embark on their life’s journey.</p>
<p><strong><em>Separating the Pups </em></strong></p>
<p>You’ll need to separate the pups once they get to around a quarter size of their mother plant.</p>
<p>Using a sharp kitchen knife or quality pair of garden sheers, carefully lay the mother plant on its side and cut away the pups. After you’ve completed this process, you’re all set to kick-start your very own air plant farm!</p>
<p><strong><em>Caring for plants after separation</em></strong></p>
<p>You’ll want to allow the cut-off point on both the mother plant and the pup to harden off for a couple of days.</p>
<p>During this time, your plants will start to recuperate from their separation. While they were growing with their mother, they may have taken on a unique (lopsided) form. In the next couple of months, you pup will start to get a more uniform shape and size. Don't worry about using plant food on pup until they have been separated for at least three months as they are quite sensitive at this time. Keep up your normal watering routine during the period. </p>
<p><strong><em>The beauty of Air Plants </em></strong></p>
<p>One of the best things about air plants is their durability and the ease in which they can be grown. They don’t need soil – just a little sunshine and water every now and then. And as you’ve seen, it’s just as simple to cultivate your air plant pups. With a little TLC, you’ll be soon be seeing a bunch of pups arrive!</p>
<p>Have a look at our selection of air plants to see for yourself how beautiful they (and their pups) can be…</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/what-on-earth-are-tillandsias</id>
    <published>2019-04-29T12:28:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:44:26-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/what-on-earth-are-tillandsias"/>
    <title>What on Earth are Tillandsias?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>So, what the heck is a Tillandsia? Whilst it might sound like a mythical creature, or something contagious you’d rather not catch, a Tillandsia is simply the scientific name of what’s more commonly known as an air plant.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/what-on-earth-are-tillandsias">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>What on Earth are Tillandsias?</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Discover the fascinating world of Tillandsias (The Scientific Name for Air Plants)</em></strong></p>
<p>So, what the heck is a Tillandsia? Whilst it might sound like a mythical creature, or something contagious you’d rather not catch, a Tillandsia is simply the scientific name of what’s more commonly known as an air plant. Air plants are found across natural environments, as well as in the gardens, patios and outdoor areas of a growing number of homes.</p>
<p><strong>Where Does the Name Come From?</strong></p>
<p>Named after Dr. Elias Tillandz, a Swedish pioneer in all thing’s botany, Tillandsia are famed for their incredible ability to grow without soil. They’re also somewhat of a collector’s item for enthusiasts and plant nerds all across the world.</p>
<p>As well as growing without the need for soil, it is the Tillandsia’s renowned ability to adapt to changing environments that has drawn both seasoned plant collectors and everyday folks to marvel at its unique quality.</p>
<p><strong>Which Plant Family Do They Originate From?</strong></p>
<p>Originating from the Bromeliad family, there’s a whopping 540 species of this awesome plant. And did you know that the world’s coolest fruit, the pineapple, is a member of the bromeliad family? It should be pointed out though, that the plants you have at home aren’t likely to be as sweet and delicious. Besides, we think they are far too beautiful to eat!</p>
<p>Over the years there’s been around 200-odd hybrids of Tillandsia that flora-aficionados have created. And there’s no doubt that in the years ahead, there’s sure to be a handful more variations of Tillandsia that crop up.</p>
<p><strong>Where Are They Naturally Found?</strong></p>
<p>These resilient plants can be found growing and thriving in an array of climates across the Americas. They have evolved to grow in the deepest jungles of the Amazon, the mountainous formations of the Rocky’s and even in the barren expanse of Central American deserts.</p>
<p><strong>Tillandsia Characteristics</strong></p>
<p>A plant’s characteristics – notably its shape and size – is largely determined by the climate in which it has grown. In a forest-type environment that is prone to significant rainfall, plants have evolved with thinner leaves. In contrast, plants that have originated in extremely dry environments have thicker, curled leaves that better contain water and are less prone to dehydration. These leaves also contain tiny white hairs called trichomes that protect the plant from sun damage. How cool is that!</p>
<p><strong>How Do They Grow Without Soil?</strong></p>
<p>No doubt you’ve found yourself wondering, <em>why aren’t these things planted in the ground? </em>After all, other plants seem to grow perfectly well in soil.</p>
<p>The fact is, Tillandsia have remarkably evolved to utilize their leaves, rather than their roots, to store moisture and nutrients. The leaves have adapted to draw in moisture from the air and to trap in water that’s used during periods of low rainfall.</p>
<p>In their natural environments - high above the earth below - these plants are protected from flooding, soil erosion and pesky little animals that might try and gobble them up.</p>
<p>The Tillandsia’s ability to thrive in just about all conditions, without the need for soil, makes them a great gift idea and a perfect plant to complement your home. But we think there’s one reason above all else that makes Tillandsia such an awesome plant. They simply look amazing!</p>
<p>Why don’t you see for yourself how a Tillandsia can spruce up the look of your garden or home TODAY.  </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/botany-encyclopedia-epiphyte</id>
    <published>2017-01-09T10:50:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:33:09-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/botany-encyclopedia-epiphyte"/>
    <title>Botany Encyclopedia: Epiphyte</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>The term </span><span class="highlight">epiphyte</span><span> refers to any plant that grows upon or attached to another living plant. The term stems from the Greek epi- (meaning 'upon') and phyton (meaning 'plant'). These plants are sometimes called </span><span class="highlight">"air plants"</span><span> because they do not root in soil.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/botany-encyclopedia-epiphyte">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span>The term </span><span class="highlight">epiphyte</span><span> refers to any plant that grows upon or attached to another living plant. The term stems from the Greek epi- (meaning 'upon') and phyton (meaning 'plant'). These plants are sometimes called </span><span class="highlight">"air plants"</span><span> because they do not root in soil. However, there are many species of algae, including seaweeds, that are epiphytes on other aquatic plants (seaweeds or aquatic angiosperms). </span></p>
<p><span>An epiphyte uses </span><span class="highlight">photosynthesis</span><span> for energy and (where non-aquatic) obtains moisture from the air or from dampness (rain and cloud moisture) on the surface of its host. </span><span class="highlight">Roots</span><span> may develop </span><span class="highlight">primarily</span><span> for attachment, and specialized structures (for example, cups and scales) used to collect or hold moisture.</span></p>
<p><span> Epiphytes are </span><span class="highlight">not parasitic</span><span> on their host, growing independently and deriving only physical support. A clear advantage is </span><span class="highlight">gained over other herbs</span><span> restricted to the ground (soil) surface where light is less available in the forest and herbivores are more active. However, epiphytes may grow so thickly as to damage the host plant. </span></p>
<p><span>The best-known epiphytes include </span><span class="highlight">mosses, lichens, orchids, and bromeliads</span><span> (such as Spanish moss and Tillandsia). Assemblages of large epiphytes occur most abundantly in moist tropical forests, but mosses and lichens occur as epiphytes in almost any environment with trees. Epiphytes are extremely important elements of tropical plant biodiversity.</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/receiving-your-new-air-plants-as-gifts</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T17:22:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:17:52-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/receiving-your-new-air-plants-as-gifts"/>
    <title>Receiving Your New Air Plants as Gifts</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>You open a box you receive the day before Christmas and it contains pretty plants but wait, they have no roots... The instructions say soak, but soak in what, where? Do I plant them? Do not plant them, do exactly as the note says, soak.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/receiving-your-new-air-plants-as-gifts">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>You open a box you receive the day before Christmas and it contains pretty plants but wait, they have no roots... The instructions say soak, but soak in what, where? Do I plant them? Do not plant them, do exactly as the note says, soak.</p>
<p>By now you have had them out of the box and doing the research so hopefully you found me at www.airplantcity.com and then you found this or you have contacted me, which you can do from the site.</p>
<p><strong>Simple steps to enjoy your Air Plant:</strong></p>
<p>1. Try to learn their names. Tillandsia Brachycoulas for instance. Go to the site and browse the product pages. Contact me with your senders email address and I can probably tell you exactly what you received.</p>
<p>2. Choose a container. Do not use a clay pot, or a deep receptacle unless you fill it up with something like marbles, pebbles or shells. The plant has to have air circulation on all parts of it and should never sit in a wet container. Get creative. You can literally use anything except copper and I don't suggest anything that can rust.</p>
<p>3. If you see unsightly roots, cut them off. I sometimes leave roots on if I think the plant would do better hanging. You can use fishing line to tie around the root, attach a hook to the other end and hang anywhere there is bright light or indirect sun light.</p>
<p>4. The tips of the airplants can be cut if they are brown on the ends, broken, or otherwise unsightly from shipping.</p>
<p>5. The most important thing to remember is that they like their bath at least once a week. Soak upside down, shake gently afterward to remove the water from between their leaves, put back in the light and enjoy...</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/transitioning-your-air-plants-from-winter-to-summer</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T17:18:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-20T14:49:07-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/transitioning-your-air-plants-from-winter-to-summer"/>
    <title>Transitioning Your Air Plants from Winter to Summer</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>As the winter months come to an end and the weather gets warmer, you have the opportunity to bring your plants outside for a summer vacation! Air plants are from tropical climates so they love the warmer weather.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/transitioning-your-air-plants-from-winter-to-summer">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>As the winter months come to an end and the weather gets warmer, you have the opportunity to bring your plants outside for a summer vacation! Air plants are from tropical climates so they love the warmer weather. Summer weather is great for air plants as more moisture comes back into the air, temperatures get warmer, and the sun shines brighter.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To help make the transition for your air plants as smooth and gentle as possible, we have a few important tips for you:</span></p>
<p><b>Do not leave them in direct sunlight.</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Be sure you place your plants in a spot that they are getting </span>indirect<span style="font-weight: 400;"> sunlight. Too much direct sunlight can burn your plant, causing the leaves to dry and wither, and can eventually kill them. If you find that one of your air plants is getting too much sun, remove it from its current location and try to find a better, shaded spot. If any leaves have dried or withered, you can use a pair of clean scissors or small gardening shears to cut off the dead and damaged parts of the leaves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Putting them on your lanai or porch is a great option, as they will be covered from direct light, but they will still get the sunlight they need. Your air plants can also be attached to to trees or other plants that have branches or leaves to shade them-- you can tie them with string onto branches or placing them in between the base of a branch and the trunk works nicely. Remember that they will not harm your trees or plants, but they might root to the host if left long enough. This might cause difficulty when it’s time to bring your air plants inside again, so just keep an eye on them! If you are worried about your plants rooting to a tree, you can always place them in a terrarium or container and hang that from the branch of a tree.</span></p>
<p><b>Air circulation is important.</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Be sure to never plant your air plants in soil because they do not take in nutrients through their roots, they absorb everything they need through their leaves. If you would like to put them in a container or terrarium, just make sure that the container doesn’t block the air circulation around any part of the plant and always remove the plant form the container to water.</span></p>
<p><b>Make sure to keep watering regularly.</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Air plants left outside will still need to be watered regularly. Continue your soaking or misting regimen, and just keep in mind that the air may be a little more humid during summer months. Make sure to check on them at least once a week to ensure that they are happy and healthy in their new location. If your plant is getting too much sun or not enough water you can adjust accordingly before it’s too late. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cut back on the fertilizer now that your air plants are outside because they will be getting natural fertilizer from birds, bugs, spiders, etc. If you notice they are looking unhappy during one of your inspections, you can soak them in a bath with a <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/products/air-plant-bromeliad-fertilizer-packet-one-year-supply">mild bromeliad fertilizer</a> for an hour or more each month.</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/winterizing-your-air-plants</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T17:13:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T09:54:14-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/winterizing-your-air-plants"/>
    <title>Winterizing Your Air Plants</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>As the weather gets colder, it’s now time to move which ever air plants you have kept outdoors into your home! Air Plants are from tropical climates so if you live up north, it will likely be necessary to bring your plants inside for the winter months.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/winterizing-your-air-plants">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the weather gets colder, it’s now time to move which ever air plants you have kept outdoors into your home! Air Plants are from tropical climates so if you live up north, it will likely be necessary to bring your plants inside for the winter months. Once the nights start falling into the 40s Farenheit, air plants should be moved indoors. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Over the summer months, your air plants received more light and higher humidity than they will during the winter. As we move them indoors, their environment will be changing in a short period of time which can put some stress on the plants. In order to cause your air plants as little stress as possible as you move them indoors, we have a few tips to help! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Temperature changes will not be too drastic for your air plants as you will be moving them inside your home where the temperature is controlled. You shouldn't be too concerned with the temperature of your home, because as long as you keep it between 55 and 85 degrees (likely for most people), your plants will be fine. It is more the change from humidity to dryness, and less sunshine, that can affect your plants and cause them some problems.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/IMG-0922_1_large.jpg?v=1522768615" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></span></p>
<p>Just be aware that if you use a heater, fireplace, wood stove, etc., the air will be a little drier. Make sure you do not place your air plants too close to the fireplace as the heat and embers can be damaging. Forced air heating can be damaging as well, so just be sure to not put your plants directly in the way of any warm air flow. Also make sure that your air plants are in an area that gets some indirect sunlight.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The dryness can be detrimental to your air plants if you do not combat it with mistings. Continue with your normal water cycle, and just add in an extra misting. You can spray directly onto the  plant, or do an air misting. Air misting is a little different than plant misting. Instead of spraying directly on the plant, just mist the air right around it to help add some humidity back into the air. Adding humidity into the air can also be done by placing some decorative bowls or shells filled with water around the plants to help with the dryness. </span></p>
<p>Another way to combat winter dryness is to decorate your bathroom with your air plants, allowing that is has bright natural light. Air plants make beautiful bathroom décor and they will get a good blast of humidity any time that someone takes a shower. You can find some pretty vases to place on your bathroom counter, or on some shelves. Another nice option is to set up a vertical garden on your bathroom walls with cork bark, a piece of wood, or any other object that you would like to cover with air plants! Just remember that a weekly soaking/watering will still be necessary even though they will get dampened from the shower humidity.</p>
<p>It is also important to consider sources for natural light in your home. Dark rooms, corridors or shelving are not ideal spots for winter survival. In the winter, you do not need to completely avoid direct sunlight, since the sun is a lot weaker and days are shorter. Try to give your air plants at least 5 hours of the winter's brightest light per day. Try to locate your air plants within 10 feet of windows. </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Make sure to not to worry too much about the transition from outdoor to indoor because as long as you keep an eye on all of your plants, especially in the beginning as you are figuring out your new watering schedule, you should be able to catch any problems early enough to fix them! For example, if you see curling leaves or dry tips, this is a sign your air plants may need a little more moisture. Just inspect them often and adjust your watering accordingly. If you are watering once a week, just up it to twice a week, in addition to your mistings, and see if that helps. If they don’t respond well enough to that change after a week or two, it could be that they are not getting enough indirect sunlight. Just try moving them to a better spot and they should improve!</span></p>
<p><strong>Other winter considerations: </strong></p>
<p><strong>Fireplaces.</strong> Make sure your plants are a good distance from the heat and embers of your fireplace.</p>
<p><strong>Air Circulation.</strong> Your plants need to have air enough to dry them after watering but should not be placed too close to a heater duct.</p>
<p><strong>Light.</strong> Bright light is important and if can't be supplied naturally then by all means use artificial lighting. Do not place your air plants too close to an incandescent bulb though and please read my article on Indoor Lighting. Also, please do not place your air plants in your Christmas Tree. The lights on the tree are hot and will burn your plants.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/help-my-air-plant-is-dying</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T17:01:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-14T16:41:42-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/help-my-air-plant-is-dying"/>
    <title>Help! My Air Plant is Dying...</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Ever feel like pulling your hair out because NOTHING you do is working and your Tillandsia are dying? We’ve all been there. Sometimes it takes a bit of experimenting to identify exactly what  the problem is and adjustments are necessary</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/help-my-air-plant-is-dying">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Ever feel like pulling your hair out because NOTHING you do is working and your Tillandsia are dying? We’ve all been there. Sometimes it takes a bit of experimenting to identify exactly what  the problem is and adjustments are necessary. Sometimes it could be out of your control, such as the weather. It could be the case that where you live is just not working for a particular species and its best to just order a different kind. If the problem is something that you can fix, take a deep breathe, stay patient, and follow our next few steps to identify the issue and turn it around!</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">First, let’s ask ourselves some questions...</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Is your air plant getting the sun that it needs? Or is it getting too much direct sunlight, causing it to dry out and burn?</span></p>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Could your air plant be getting not enough, or too much water? </span></p>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Where do you live and what time of year is it? </span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These questions are a great place to start. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s talk about sunlight!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Signs of sunburn include brown spots, dried out patches appearing on inside growth, and very unhealthy splotchy appearance of outside leaves. Signs of not enough sun are harder to see, but could include falling leaves, and leaves cupping inward.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If your air plant is outdoors, make sure that it is shaded by something and not receiving too much direct sunlight. If you suspect this could be the case, try moving it to a more covered area, or bringing it inside for the time being while it regains it health. If your air plant is inside, make sure that is is getting access to enough natural sunlight or at least indoor fluorescent lighting. Try putting your air plant near a window. We recommend keeping them in south or north facing windows, as they will get more indirect sunlight than east or west. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now, if you think that the sunlight is not the problem, let’s take a look at your watering schedule. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Signs of not enough water include curling leaves, and drying tips, while signs of too much watering could be some browning (rotting) on the bottom base of the plant. Inspect your plant to see if any of the signs are present. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you suspect your air plant is thirsty, try giving it an immediate soaking for an hour or more. Let your plant fully dry before placing it back in its usual spot. From there try adding in an extra soaking or some mistings into your watering routine.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If its the other way around and you decide that your plant is being over watered, try removing the mistings from you watering cycle, or adding a few days between soaks. You should also inspect your air plant to make sure that it does not have any water sitting in its inner crevices. This is one of the main causes of rotting in air plants. Next time you water, gently shake out the plant and place it upside down, like a cup, to allow it to properly dry and do not place it back in to a terrarium or container until it is completely dry. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep in mind that where you live and what time of year it is could greatly influence the above factors. Generally if it is winter, the air will be dryer, the sun will be less strong, and if it is summer, it will be more humid and the sun will be at its strongest. You can use this information along with the physical appearance of your plant to help you decide which steps to take in trying to get your air plants back to a healthy state. </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-watering-tap-water-or-not</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T16:56:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-20T14:48:24-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-watering-tap-water-or-not"/>
    <title>How to Water Air Plants</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Although air plants are generally very easy plants to care for, watering tends to be the make or break factor. Don’t worry though! We have some tips and tricks to make it easy and simple.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plant-watering-tap-water-or-not">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although air plants are generally very easy plants to care for, watering tends to be the make or break factor. Don’t worry though! We have some tips and tricks to make it easy and simple. </span></p>
<p><strong>What type of water to use?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In their natural habitat, air plants get their nutrients from rain water, bird droppings, and dying bugs. If you can collect rainwater, this would be the best option, or if you have access to pond, creek, lake, or well water.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If not, the next best option is spring water. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You don’t want to use tap water or filtered water. City tap water tends to have less minerals and more chemicals. Filtered water has been stripped of many of the natural minerals and nutrients that are beneficial to air plants.</span></p>
<p><strong>To soak or to mist?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is best to soak your air plants for 20 minutes to an hour every week to 10 days, with a supplemental misting depending on current climate and time of year. The water should be lukewarm, as cold or hot water will shock the air plants. If you decide to solely mist your air plants, make sure to do this about once a day, less or more when needed. When you mist your plants, make sure to spray all of the leaves enough to wet them, but not to the point that they are dripping.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After a soaking or misting, it is extremely important to make sure your air plants can completely dry, especially before placing them back into a terrarium or container. To ensure your air plants dry, place them in some indirect sunlight. You can place them upside down on top of a towel to let the water drip down the leaves, similar to drying a cup. Allow a few hours for the plant to fully dry, as air plants are very susceptible to rotting if they are left wet too long. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The hardest part about watering is understanding that what your air plant needs depends largely on its environment, and we’re here to help!</span></p>
<p><strong>What time of year is it? Are you running your heater often? Do you live in a humid or drier climate? </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are all factors that can help you better determine how much water your air plants need. If you live in a drier climate, your plant will need to be watered more frequently than if you live somewhere with more humidity.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Watering can also depend on the time of year. During summer, the air is hotter and dryer, so you will need to water more. During Winter, your air plants will need a little less water because it will be cooler and more humid. Although if you are running a heater or using a fireplace, this will dry the air a little bit as well.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Follow these simple tips and tricks, and your air plants will thrive.</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/hot-summer-sun-air-plants</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T12:27:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-20T14:49:38-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/hot-summer-sun-air-plants"/>
    <title>Hot Sun &amp; Air Plants: How to Find the Happy Medium</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>As we have mentioned before, air plants do best with indirect sunlight. Too much sunlight will deplete the moisture from your air plants, and cause them to burn and eventually die if they are left in the sun too long.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/hot-summer-sun-air-plants">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As we have mentioned before, air plants do best with indirect sunlight. Too much sunlight will deplete the moisture from your air plants, and cause them to burn and eventually die if they are left in the sun too long. Air plant leaves are covered in tiny scales, properly called <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/air-plant-articles/air-plants-trichomes" title="Air Plant Trichomes">trichomes</a>, that serve two major functions. First, they assist the plant in absorbing water and nutrients. Second, they help to reflect sunlight off of the leaf surface.</span></p>
<div style="text-align: left;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/trichomes_tectorum_ecuador_air_plant_grande.jpg?v=1566507634" style="float: none; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">The bright, white, and long trichomes of <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/frontpage/products/tillandsia-tectorum-ecuador-air-plants">Tectorum Ecuador</a> help it to reflect the bright light in its natural, exposed habitat. This species can be found at high elevation cliff faces in Peru and Ecuador.</span></em></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Generally, you want to keep all of your air plants out of direct sunlight as much as possible, however, some tillandsia can take more sun than others depending on the species of the plant and its environment. If your plant has thinner, wispier leaves, then it probably will not do too well in direct sunlight. Thicker, fuller leaves can hold moisture better so this type of air plant may better tolerate some direct sunlight for portions of the day. The air plant species that have silver leaves, such as xerographica, tend to do best handling direct sunlight.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you live in a southern state or desert area where the sun is very strong, you should be very cautious with exposing your air plants to direct sunlight. Be especially careful in areas that lack humidity, like the desert, as your plants will damage and dry out from the direct sunlight even quicker. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you keep your air plants indoors, we would recommend keeping them close to windows. They could also be kept near a window that is shaded, either from a tree or any other kind of protection from the direct sun. A lot of people also like to keep their air plants in an office with either indirect sunlight from windows, or bright fluorescent lighting. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you keep your air plants outside, just follow the same guidelines, and be sure they are in an area the the sun won’t directly hit for more than an hour per day, or where they are shaded completely from direct sunlight. Under a tree or on your porch or lanai should work great!</span></p>
<div><span><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/air_plants_tillandsia_outdoors_1_grande.jpg?v=1566507028" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></span></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><em><span>Shaded porches or patios that only get light in the mornings and late afternoons are a great place for air plants.</span></em></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><em><span></span></em></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Signs of sunburn include brown spots, dried out patches appearing on inside growth, and very unhealthy splotchy appearance of outside leaves where totally wet. If you notice any of these signs, immediately take the plant out of its current location and be prepared to do some light maintenance. Gently pull off the outside leaves that are totally damaged. If they do not remove easily, use a pair of scissors to trim off damaged areas. Now that you have removed the most damaged parts of the plant, give the air plant a good soaking before finding it a new spot that’s better out of the sun. Do not fertilize the air plant until it is completely healthy again, just continue with your watering schedule and add a few daily, light mistings. Don’t over soak as the plant can come apart if it stays wet for too long. Just be patient and consistent and your air plant should get back to its happy, healthy self in no time! </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
