<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs.atom"/>
  <title>Air Plant City - Air Plant City News &amp; Updates</title>
  <updated>2021-05-31T10:46:02-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Air Plant City</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/corporate-gift-guide</id>
    <published>2021-05-31T10:46:02-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-31T10:58:05-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/corporate-gift-guide"/>
    <title>Your Simplified Corporate Gift Guide</title>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Chorneyko</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Whether you work from home or in an office, plants are a lively way to spruce up any workspace. Air plants are the perfect gift for any colleague – not only do they brighten up your space, but they are also low-maintenance plants that will last a very long time.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/corporate-gift-guide">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Green Corporate Gifting Just Got Easier</span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether you work from home or in an office, plants are a lively way to spruce up any workspace. Air plants are the perfect gift for any colleague – not only do they brighten up your space, but they are also low-maintenance plants that will last a very long time (hopefully). In light of the pandemic, we have improved our corporate gifting fulfillment services. Some of our benefits include: <br> </span>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Corporate ordering incentives for early orders </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">More options for employee gifts</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">More personalization options for your gifts</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A stress-free fulfillment service </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">All-in pricing (including shipping) starting at $9.95/person</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scheduling your shipments in advance for synchronized arrival</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A great way to show appreciation to your team </span></li>
</ul>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our Most Popular Corporate Gifts </span></h3>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_glass_terrarium_trio_7_1.jpg?v=1622471237" alt="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: none;"></div>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3 itemprop="name" class="product-details-product-title" style="text-align: center;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/wholesale-gifts-displays-containers/products/wholesale-stunning-flat-bottom-globe-glass-terrariums-with-2-air-plants-each-moss-and-stones" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia terrarium corporate gift care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stunning Glass Terrariums with 2 Air Plants Each. Includes Red Abdita, Moss and Stones</a></span></h3>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplantcity_tillandsia_airplants-Driftwood-198.jpg?v=1622471771" alt="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: none;"> </p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3 itemprop="name" class="product-details-product-title"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/wholesale-gifts-displays-containers/products/wholesale-wooden-driftwood-containers-with-red-abdita-air-plant" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Small Wooden Driftwood Containers with Assorted Air Plants</a></span></h3>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/Airplants_tillandsia_containers4.jpg?v=1622471495" alt="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3 itemprop="name" class="product-details-product-title"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/wholesale-gifts-displays-containers/products/wholesale-wooden-driftwood-containers-with-custom-air-plants?variant=35929135427" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Large Wooden Driftwood Containers with Custom Air Plants</a></span></h3>
<p><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_teardrop_terrarium_18.jpg?v=1622472001" alt="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: none;"> </p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3 itemprop="name" class="product-details-product-title"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/wholesale-gifts-displays-containers/products/wholesale-teardrop-terrariums-with-river-stones-and-ionantha-air-plants" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Teardrop Terrariums with River Stones and Ionantha Air Plants</a></span></h3>
<p> <img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1681/0005/files/airplants_tillandsia_geometric_iron_pendant_12_7d35a09f-9bc2-4273-8cb9-3810cd223843.jpg?v=1622472134" alt="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" style="margin: 20px 20px 20px 20px; float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3 itemprop="name" class="product-details-product-title"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/wholesale-gifts-displays-containers/products/wholesale-geometric-pendants-hangers-with-assorted-air-plants" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia corporate gift care" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hanging Metal Pendants with Assorted Air Plants</a></span></h3>
</div>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why Gift Air Plants? </span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Plants provide air for indoor spaces, but they are also mood-boosters. Not to mention they are known to increase productivity and creativity, making them ideal for a home or office setting. Employees will be excited to display their unique gifts. Plus, gifting plants is an easy way to show employees or team members how much you appreciate their hard work during a stressful times. Choose from a large selection of air plants, terrarium, and container options to show your employees how valued they are!</span>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Personalize Your Gifts With Marketing and Branding Options </span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Get creative with your gifting by sending us any stickers, drop cards, thank you cards, and custom tape you’d like to include with your gifts. If it fits, we are happy to include it to make sure your gifts feel as personal as possible. We even have options to attach personalized messages on the loop of the air plant, terrarium, ceramic vase, or metal pendant of your choosing. <br> </span><br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All gifts are customizable to your budget! We also include an air plant care card with every plant to make following <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-care" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care corporate gifting" rel="noopener noreferrer">care instructions</a> easy. If you’d like to include company branding and marketing, it can be sent to us and included in shipments. <br> </span><b> <br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><span>Email us at </span><a href="mailto:service@airplantcity.com" title="service@airplantcity.com"><span><strong>service@airplantcity.com</strong> </span></a><span>or call us at </span><strong>(904) 429-5716 </strong>to connect with a team member and get a quote.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Shipping Options </span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">When it comes to shipping your gifts, you can use our shipping services, or you can use your own corporate UPS or FedEx account to ensure they arrive on time. We back all shipments with our <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-guarantee" target="_blank" title="air plant tillandsia care corporate gifting" rel="noopener noreferrer">30-Day Replacement Plant Guarantee</a> in the case of any issues during shipping. We provide you with an Excel template to make submitting your recipient list simple, and we will happily schedule your shipment to fit your schedule. Order in advance and we will take care of the fulfillment and shipping so that the plants arrive as fresh as possible. Keep in mind that our air plants can only be shipped to U.S. residents and we also require a minimum order of 50 recipients. <br> </span><br><span style="font-weight: 400;"><span>Email us at </span><a href="mailto:service@airplantcity.com" title="service@airplantcity.com"><span><strong>service@airplantcity.com</strong> </span></a><span>or call us at </span><strong>(904) 429-5716</strong> to get a custom quote! </span>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/air-plant-farming-that-s-kind-to-the-environment</id>
    <published>2019-06-26T12:53:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-20T15:02:01-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/air-plant-farming-that-s-kind-to-the-environment"/>
    <title>Air Plant Farming That’s Kind to the Environment</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>There are times when our customers ask us about our sustainability practices. They will want to know how we cultivate our Tillandsias and what effect, if any, there is on the plant’s natural environment</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/air-plant-farming-that-s-kind-to-the-environment">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>Air Plant Farming That’s Kind to the Environment</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>We ensure that all our air plants are farmed and collected in an environmentally friendly manner. </em></strong></p>
<p>There are times when our customers ask us about our sustainability practices. They will want to know how we cultivate our Tillandsias and what effect, if any, there is on the plant’s natural environment. Given that our customers are environmentally conscious consumers that share our love of nature, it’s to be expected that they would ask these questions.</p>
<p><strong><em>We source and grow our air plants in only the most environmentally conscious way. </em></strong></p>
<p>Native Tillandsia are most commonly found in tropical parts of the Americas. They have long been seen by people as a prized piece of native flora. So much so, that some species, including Harrisii and Xerographica, came close to extinction several decades ago. This forced the hand of regulators who made it illegal to source these beautiful plants from their native environment.</p>
<p>At present, exporters of Tillandsia must prove to their agricultural department that plants were nursery grown and not collected from the wild. This has led to a slight rejuvenation of plant numbers in the wild.</p>
<p>After the implementation of these restrictions, growers have developed enhanced methods of producing these protected species in a nursery environment. This has increased their growth rate and made it possible for more consumers to enjoy these gorgeous plants in their homes.</p>
<p><strong><em>What does this mean for us and our customers?</em></strong></p>
<p>This means that first and foremost, we will only work alongside suppliers that have been certified by their governments for Tillandsia exportation. By doing this, we are proud to support sustainable practices that benefit environmentally conscious suppliers.</p>
<p><strong><em>Why not place an order today</em></strong></p>
<p>The next time you order a stunning air plant from us, not only will you be able to enjoy its beautiful color and aesthetic appeal; you’ll know that it was grown and collected in an environmentally friendly way.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/are-you-searching-for-a-business-idea</id>
    <published>2019-06-26T12:42:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-20T15:00:51-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/are-you-searching-for-a-business-idea"/>
    <title>Are You Searching for a Business Idea?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Scott James</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Not only do we provide our gorgeous range of air plants to our retail customers; we also offer our beautiful plants to re-sellers and commercial businesses. Whether you’re just starting out your side business or you’re a larger, established supplier, we can help you with our amazing range of plants.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.airplantcity.com/blogs/featured-blogs/are-you-searching-for-a-business-idea">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>Are You Searching for a Business Idea?</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Why not become an air plant re-seller?</em></strong></p>
<p>Not only do we provide our gorgeous range of air plants to our retail customers; we also offer our beautiful plants to re-sellers and commercial businesses. Whether you’re just starting out your side business or you’re a larger, established supplier, we can help you with our amazing range of plants. And all the products come with our unrivaled customer service and a <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/air-plant-guarantee" title="Our Guarantee ">30-day guarantee</a>.</p>
<p><strong><em>How long until plants arrive? </em></strong></p>
<p>After you’ve placed the order you can sit back and relax, knowing that our turnaround time is <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/shipping" title="Our Fast Shipping">incredibly fast</a>. All orders will generally arrive in only 3-5 days from the time the order is placed. If you need it sooner, opt for our express service at checkout, which guarantees a 2 day delivery by either FedEx or UPS for a $30 flat rate.</p>
<p><strong><em>Who choose air plants?</em></strong></p>
<p>Air plants are a great way of adding some colors and a stylish look to all types of environments. Perhaps you have a homewares gift store? Or it could simply be a craft stall at a farmer’s market. A selection of carefully placed air plants will make your store even more appealing. And as well as being easy to look after, air plants don’t create a mess! You can admire them without having to worry about cleaning up a bunch of soil.</p>
<p><strong><em>We sell wholesale to florists</em></strong></p>
<p>Many florists across the country are now featuring our stunning range of air plants. And it makes sense, with more and more customers purchasing Tillandsia for their homes.</p>
<p><strong><em>30-day guarantee</em></strong></p>
<p>Our exclusive 30-day guarantee can be used for your customers too. That’s why we recommend our re-sellers always offer a 30-day guarantee for their customers. If there are issues, such as a plant being damaged, let us know and we can send you a replacement for your next order. This is sure to put your customers at ease and will most likely lead to repeat business for many years to come!</p>
<p><strong><em>We can customize our selection of air plants </em></strong> </p>
<p>Our plants come in a diverse range of different sizes and styles. Depending on your requirements, we can customize a collection of plants that your customers are sure to love. We can include our most popular air plants, including the gorgeous <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/all-wholesale-air-plants-gifts-terrariums-containers-for-tillandsia/products/wholesale-jumbo-xerographica-10-16-inch-plants" title="Wholesale Xerographica">Xerographica</a>, and arrange them in a beautiful collection.</p>
<p>We also offer our wholesale customers a stunning range of terrarium kits, variety packs that feature a colorful range of different species, and single species.</p>
<p>Check out our <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/collections/all-wholesale-air-plants-gifts-terrariums-containers-for-tillandsia" title="Wholesale Air Plants">wholesale page</a> for a look at our plants, as well as all the latest specials. Prices are featured on our website. If you have more questions about our wholesale program, visit our <a href="https://www.airplantcity.com/pages/wholesale-air-plant" title="Wholesale Air Plants | Tillandsia | FAQ">Wholesale FAQ Page</a>.</p>
<p>Your customers will adore them!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
